Natick, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1721-1920.
Congregational Library & Archives
Natick, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1721-1920.
RG4839
Congregational Library & Archives
1.15 Cubic Feet
(1 box, 3 reels)
First Congregational Church of Natick, Massachusetts, was established in 1651 by a group of English settlers and missionaries under the leadership of Rev. John Elliot. The church became home to many local Native Americans, also known as "Praying Indians," and was the location of the writing of the "Eliot Bible:" a bible translated into phonetic Algonquian. This collection contains records of church covenants, meeting minutes, baptismal records, lists of deaths, disciplinary records, ordinations, and membership records.
First Congregational Church (Natick, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
The 1721-1794 church record book was deposited at the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church of Natick in 2007; no accession number.
The remaining portion of the collection was deposited at the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church of Natick in 2016; accession 2016-05. This accession was originally provided the identifier RG5313.
Digital Copies
Records within this collection were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions may be accessed online through our digital archive.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The First Congregational Church in Natick was established by a group of English settlers and missionaries led by Rev. John Eliot in 1651, in what is now old South Natick. The settlers cultivated strong relationships with local Indigenous peoples, mainly comprising members of the Massachusett tribe, while attempting to convert them to Christianity. To this end, Rev. Eliot studied the Algonquin language with the help of the Montaukett interpreter Cockenoe, eventually publishing a translation of the Bible in phonetic Algonquin.
Those who converted were known as "Praying Indians" and became foundational members of the First Church in Natick, which was typified by its racially diverse congregation during the 17th and 18th centuries. There was a sizeable minority of congregants who were identified as "Negro" in the earliest church registers, as well as increasing numbers of white members. The Native presence persisted despite major fluctuations in their numbers, including those resulting from deadly forced removals to Deer Island in 1675, during King Philip's War.
In 1721 the old meetinghouse was rebuilt and local missionary Rev. Oliver Peabody was appointed as minister. During his tenure (1721-1752), he created the first extant records for both the church and town. Construction on a third meetinghouse in the same location began in 1754.
By 1749 however, white congregants were lobbying to move the church from South Natick to the increasingly segregated Natick Center. These "Center Members" were at odds with the largely Indigenous South Natick members who wished to retain the old location. Despite the unifying efforts of Rev. Peabody's successor, Rev. Stephen Badger, a fourth meetinghouse was eventually built in Natick Center in 1767. In 1798 the congregation officially split, largely (although not completely) along racial lines, with both groups retaining the moniker of "First Church". Rev. Badger was subsequently dismissed for his refusal to preach at the Center church, continuing to reside in South Natick until his death in 1803.
After the congregational schism, the South Natick division of Natick First fell into disrepair, but was revived in 1828 with the incorporation of the South Parish Congregational Church and the construction of a new meeting house. The South Parish, which became Unitarian in 1870, is now called the Eliot Church and hosts a revived Praying Indian community of worship. The "Center" church continued through several physical iterations until the present day while retaining the designation of the First Church in Natick. Notable among these was the sixth meetinghouse, a costly edifice erected on the same site in 1854, which included a bell and fine organ, and played host to several prominent luminaries of the Civil War era. This structure however burned down only two decades after its construction, in the great Natick fire of 1874. A gothic-style church was erected adjacent to the former site in 1877 and is still in use. Natick First joined the United Church of Christ shortly after the latter organization's foundation in 1957.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains early administrative and financial records for the First Congregational Church in Natick. The collection contains administrative records and meeting minutes, financial records and ledgers, church membership records, baptismal records, marriage records, records of deaths, sermons produced by Benjamin Caryl, church correspondence, a list of prohibition supporters, and a history of the Sabbath school in Natick.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection have been arranged in chronological order by start date.
Technical Requirements
To access digital materials on our digital archive, it is strongly recommended that you use the latest available version of Microsoft Edge, Google Chrome, Mozilla Firefox, or Safari (Apple).
A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
Algonquin Indians.; Baptismal records.; Church discipline.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Covenants (Church polity).; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Ordination.; Sermons, American -- Early works to 1800.; Temperance and religion.; Badger, Stephen, 1726-1803; First Congregational Church (Natick, Mass.); Natick (Mass.) -- Church history; Peabody, Oliver, 1698-1752; Sears, Freeman, 1779-1811; South Congregational Church in Natick (Natick, Mass.)
- Church records, 1721 1794; 1721-1794 (Box 1, Volume 1, Reel Print Master, Reel Archival Master, Reel Service Copy)
  Scope and Contents
  This volume contains the earliest extant records for the town of Natick and of the First Church. They begin in 1721, the year in which a second meetinghouse was built and in which Rev. Oliver Peabody began his 30 year tenure. It includes lists of members, baptisms, deaths, church meetings minutes, and a copy of the church covenant. This volume of records includes a list of "those Indians that have Dyed from among us," which can be used as an index to track the activities of Native Americans in the church, many of whom had anglicized names. Stewardship of the records passed to Rev. Stephen Badger in 1752, after Rev. Peabody's death.
  Restrictions on Access
  Of the microfilm reels, only the service copy is available for public use. Master reels are restricted and maintained for preservation purposes.
- Letter regarding the building of the third meeting house, 1750 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Physical Access
  Access to this folder is restricted due to the presence of broken glass. Contact the archivist for special permission to view the item. Special gloves must be worn when handling this folder.
- Letter to bereaved parent, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This single piece of correspondence is both unsigned and unaddressed. Its writer expresses sympathy with a bereaved parent whose son was killed in the disastrous defeat of General Edward Braddock's forces near Fort Duquesne, in the "Battle of the Monongahela" during the French and Indian War. The letter was sent from Boston and dated August 4, 1755.
- Warrant for meeting about gallery stairs, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Access to this folder is limited due to the presence of glass. Handle with care.
- Benjamin Caryl sermons, 1762 1803; 1762-1803 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "A sermon at the execution of Moses Paul", circa 1772 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Electronic resource available
  An electronic version of a later edition of this sermon is available through Hathi Trust Digital Library: A Sermon at the execution of Moses Paul
  Library resource available
  A different edition of this item is available from the Congregational Library & Archives: 15.5 5842.1
  Access to this item is restricted due to the fragility of the object. Please use either the edition held by the library or the electronic version on Hathi Trust. Contact the archivist for special permission to view this item.
- A plan of Concert of Prayer circular letter, 1794 1795; 1794-1795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Purchase of town's right to meeting house, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Church records, 1802 1833; 1802-1833 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  This volume dates from shortly after the Church's 1798 schism and comprises the records of the "Center" division of Natick First. It includes details of the church's committee at the time of formation, articles of faith, the church covenant, financial records, member lists, records of baptisms, marriages, deaths, church meeting minutes, and correspondence. The death records include detailed mortality information such as age at death and cause of death, and occasional demographic details. Correspondence includes a letter from Rev. Sears seeking reconciliation with the people of South Natick. A table of contents is included at the front of the volume.
- Ministerial fund records, 1802 1914; 1802-1914 (Box 1, Volume 3)
- Freeman Sears letter, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Financial records, 1814 1914; 1814-1914 (Box 1, Volume 4)
- "A sermon, delivered at Natick, January 5, 1817, containing a history of said town" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  An electronic version of this item is available through the Internet Archives: "A Sermon, delivered at Natick, January 5, 1817"
  This sermon was authored by Martin Moore, but it includes an end note which was authored by Freeman Sears, minister at the First Congregational Church of Natick between 1806 and 1811.
- Financial records, 1822 1862; 1822-1862 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  This volume comprises financial ledgers from Natick First's 'Center' church subsequent to the congregational split of 1798. The records, kept by various of the church's treasurers, detail incoming and outgoing revenue, ministerial salaries, member rates, and other miscellaneous expenses.
- Church records, 1833 1864; 1833-1864 (Box 1, Volume 6)
- Daniel Wight papers, 1837 1919; 1837-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Church records by Willard Drury, 1856 1868; 1856-1868 (Box 1, Volume 7)
- Financial records, 1861 1866; 1861-1866 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Typewritten excerpt from "The old Indian chronicle", 1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  A complete copy of the work this item is an excerpt of is available through the Hathi Trust Digital Library: "The old Indian chronicle: being a collection of exceeding rare tracts written and published in the time of King Philip's war"
  This typewritten excerpt contains the text of pages 88 through 96 from "The old Indian chronicle", a work by Samuel G. Grace.
- Financial records, 1878 1912; 1878, 1900-1912 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Separated Materials
  These materials were removed from the volume "Financial records, 1814-1914".
- Prohibition supporters, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chronological list of members from 1802-1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This list of members was compiled by Lucy E. Wight.
- Early history of the Natick Sabbath School, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)